Karim Pérez Martínez

PHD IN PRODUCTION ENGINEERING - OPERATIONS RESEARCH

Profile ____

Researcher with over 3 years of experience in developing specialized optimization algorithms for operations planning. My professional experiences are mainly concentrated in the application of optimization techniques to operations planning in manufacturing, and developing of decomposition methods for optimization problems. I have also trained on data visualization, classical machine learning, deep learning and reinforcement learning algorithms. My skills include developing with Python, Optimization solvers as CPLEX and Gurobi, programming libraries and tools such as Matplotlib, Pandas, Numpy, Scikit Learn, Tensorflow, and Keras. My research interests include:

- Supply Chain and Operations Management
- Optimization of Production Planning Decisions in Manufacturing
- Prescriptive, Predictive and Descriptive Analytics
- Mathematical Programming and Decomposition Techniques for Discrete Optimization
- Integration of Machine Learning and Operations Research Techniques

Languages _____

- Spanish Mother tongue
- English Advanced
- Portuguese Advanced
- French Upper-Intermediate. TCF C1 Oral comprehension, TCF B2 Oral production (2020)

Education _____

Ph.D. in Production Engineering

June 2018

Federal University of São Carlos, Brazil Specialization: Operations Research

M.Sc. in Production Engineering

September 2013

FEDERAL UNIVERSITY OF SÃO CARLOS, BRAZIL

Specialization: Production Systems Management

B.Eng. in Industrial Engineering

December 2011

University of Córdoba, Colombia

Professional Developement _____

2021	Machine Learning Strategy and Intro to Reinforcement Learning ,	Stanford
	AI Professional Program at Stanford Engineering School	
2020	Introduction to Deep Learning & Neural Networks with Keras , \ensuremath{IBM}	Issued by Coursera
	Machine Learning with Python, IBM	Issued by Coursera
2019	Summer School in Deep Learning, The Institute for Data Valorization (IVADO) /Mila	Montreal, CA
	Data Analysis and Visualization in Python, IVADO/Calcul Québec	Montreal, CA
	GPU Computing with Python, Calcul Québec	Montreal, CA
	Machine Learning, Stanford	Issued by Coursera
	Data Visualization and Data Analysis with Python, IBM	Issued by Coursera
	Python for Data Science and AI, IBM	Issued by Coursera
2018	Software Development for Research, Calcul Québec	Montreal, CA

Scholarships & Grants _____

GERAD Postdoctoral Scholarship

Canada

GROUP FOR RESEARCH IN DECISION ANALYSIS (GERAD) - CAD 25,000.00

June 2018

FAPESP Research Internship Abroad Scholarship (BEPE)

Brazi

SÃO PAULO RESEARCH FOUNDATION (FAPESP) - CAD 34,000

May 2016 - May 2017

FAPESP Ph.D. Scholarship

DIGZII

SÃO PAULO RESEARCH FOUNDATION (FAPESP) - CAD 45,500

Oct. 2014-Feb. 2018

National Ph.D. Scholarship - Social Demand

Brazil

COORDINATION FOR THE IMPROVEMENT OF HIGHER EDUCATION PERSONNEL (CAPES) - CAD 5,000

March 2014 - Aug. 2014

National M.Sc. Scholarship - Social Demand

Brazi

COORDINATION FOR THE IMPROVEMENT OF HIGHER EDUCATION PERSONNEL (CAPES) - CAD 14,000

Sept. 2011 - Aug. 2013

Research Experiences _____

GERAD, CIRRELT & HEC Montréal

Montreal, CA

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER

June 2018 - Present

- Developing exact solution methods for a variety of integrated production planning problems
- · Preparing and writing scientific papers for submission to peer-reviewed journals
- Preparing and delivering presentations at GERAD and international conferences

CIRRELT & HEC Montréal

Montreal, CA

VISITING PH.D. STUDENT

May 2016 - May 2017

- · Developing exact solution methods to solve a real production planning problem in the Molded Pulp Packaging Industry
- · Auditing Ph.D. courses at HEC Montréal
- Preparing and writing scientific papers for submission to peer-reviewed journals
- · Attending, preparing, and delivering oral presentations at CIRRELT, national, and international conferences

Federal University of São Carlos & SANOVO Greenpack

Sorocaba, Brazil

Ph.D. Researcher Student

May. 2014 - Aug. 2016

- Modeling and analysing the production planning process in the company
- Collecting real data to validate and test the developed mathematical models
- Validating and discussing results with the production planning team of the company

Federal University of São Carlos & Recycling center CATARES

Sorocaba, Brazil

VISITING UNDERGRADUATE STUDENT

March. 2011 - Dec. 2011

- Modeling and analysing the waste colection process in the city
- Collecting real data to validate and test the mathematical models
- Validating and discussing results with stakeholders in the recycling center

Teaching Experiences _____

HEC Montréal - Master of Science Program

Montreal, Canada

TEACHING ASSISTANT OF THE COURSE "SUPPLY CHAIN ANALYTICS"

Winter 2021

- Preparing coding workshop's material
- · Creating Python notebooks with examples and exercises of analytics techniques applied to supply chain problems

HEC Montréal - B. in Business Administration

PART-TIME LECTURER OF THE COURSE "OPERATIONS MANAGEMENT"

Montreal, Canada Winter 2020 and 2021

- · Delivering lectures to the students in accordance with the syllabus created by the department
- · Conducting office hours on a regular basis to discuss grades, assignments, and other issues with the students
- · Grading assignments and exams

Federal University of São Carlos - B.Eng. in Production Engineering

TEACHING ASSISTANT OF THE COURSE "OPERATIONAL RESEARCH TO PRODUCTION ENGINEERING I"
TEACHING ASSISTANT OF THE COURSE "OPERATIONAL RESEARCH TO PRODUCTION ENGINEERING II"

TEACHING ASSISTANT OF THE COURSE "OPERATIONAL RESEARCH II"

- · Assisting the course instructor with class preparation and course materials
- · Conducting office hours on a regular basis to discuss assignments and lab activities with the students

São Carlos and Sorocaba, Braz

Aug. 2017 - Dec. 2017 March 2014 (2015) - July 2014 (2015)

March 2012 - July 2012

Professional Services _____

Reviewing

- Computers & Operations Research Journal
- Applied Mathematical Modelling Journal
- European Journal of Operational Research
- Journal Pesquisa Operacional
- Brazilian National Conference on Computational and Applied Mathematics (CNMAC)
- Brazilian Symposium on Operations Research (SBPO)
- Brazilian Workshop on Cutting and Packing Problems, Production Planning, and Related Problems (ONPCE)

Research Events Organization

• Brazilian Workshop on Cutting and Packing Problems, Production Planning, and Related problems (ONPCE)

Member of M.Sc. Jury

• Nov. 2019. Member of the jury. Qualification exam and final defense of the M.Sc. candidate Cindy Lobo. Dept. of Production Engineering, Federal University of São Carlos, Brazil.

Co-supervising

 Oct. 2019 - Jan. 2020. Visiting undergraduate student João Gabriel Hernandes at HEC Montréal. Research project: Reverse Logistics Planning of Waste Electrical and Electronic Equipment (WEEE) in Brazil with Financial and Environmental Objectives.

Publications _____

Works in progress

- Pérez Martínez, K.; Adulyasak, Y. and Jans, R. Enhanced Logic-based Benders Decomposition for Printing Planning under Uncertain Demand.
- · Melega, G.; Pérez Martínez, K. Formulations for integrated process selection and lot sizing problems.

Accepted for publication

• Pérez Martínez, K.; Adulyasak, Y. and Jans, R. 2019. Logic-based Benders decomposition for integrated process configuration and production planning problems. Submitted to INFORMS Journal on Computing (Technical report, Les Cahiers du GERAD G-2019-73, GERAD. October 2019).

Papers in International Journals

- Martínez, K. P.; Adulyasak, Y.; Jans, R.; Morabito, R. and Toso, E. A. V. 2019. An exact optimization approach for an integrated process configuration, lot-sizing and scheduling problem. Computers & Operations Research, 103, 310–323
- Martínez, K. P.; Morabito, R., and Toso, E. A. V. 2018. A coupled process configuration, lot sizing and scheduling model for production planning in the molded pulp industry. *International Journal of Production Economics*, 204, 227–243
- Martínez, K. P., Toso, E. A., Morabito, R., 2016. Production planning in the molded pulp packaging industry. *Computers & Industrial Engineering*, 98, 544–566
- Martínez, K. P.; Toso, E. A. V., 2016. Lot sizing and scheduling in the molded pulp packaging industry. Gestão & Produção 23(3), 649-660

Conferences & Oral Presentations

Invited Talks

- "Logic-based Benders reformulations and algorithms for process configuration and production planning problems". *Group for Research in Decision Analysis (GERAD)*. Montreal, Canada. May, 2019
- "Exact and heuristic approaches for an integrated process configuration, lot sizing and scheduling problem". *Interuniversity Research Centre on the Enterprise Networks, Logistics and Transportation (CIRRELT)*. Montreal, Canada. April, 2017

Regular Presentations

- "Solving process configurations and production planning problems" with Y. Adulyasak and R. Jans. In: 2019 INFORMS Annual Meeting. October 20-23. Seattle, United States
- "Logic-based Benders reformulations and algorithms for process configurations and production planning problems" with Y. Adulyasak and R. Jans. In: 2019 INFORMS ALIO International Conference. June 9-12. Cancún, México
- "Logic-based Benders reformulations and algorithms for process configurations and production planning problems", with Y. Adulyasak and R. Jans. In: *Optimization Days 2019*. May 13-15. Montreal, Canada
- "Solution approaches for an integrated process configuration, lot-sizing and scheduling problem in the packaging industry", with Y. Adulsayak, R. Jans, E. Toso and R. Morabito. In: 2017 INFORMS Annual Meeting. October 22–25, 2017. Houston, United States
- "Planning and scheduling processes in the molded pulp packaging industry", with E. Toso and R. Morabito. In: 58th Annual conference of the Canadian Operational Research Society. May 30–June 1, 2016. Banff, Canada
- "An optimization model for generating molding patterns and production planning in the molded pulp industry", with E. Toso and R. Morabito. In: XVII Brazilian Workshop on Cutting and Packing Problems, Production planning and related problems (ONPCE). June 11–12, 2015. Sorocaba, Brazil
- "Lot sizing and scheduling: A case study in a Brazilian packaging company", with E. Toso. In: XV Brazilian Workshop on Cutting and Packing Problems, Production planning and related problems (ONPCE). March 21–22, 2013. São José de Rio Preto, Brazil

Peer-reviewed Conference Proceedings

- "Mathematical models for production planning and scheduling in the molded pulp packaging industry", with E. Toso and R. Morabito. In: XLVI Brazilian Symposium on Operations Research. September 16–19, 2014. Salvador, Brazil
- "Planejamento e Programação da Produção na Indústria de Embalagens em Polpa Moldada", with E. Toso. In: XLV Brazilian Symposium on Operations Research. September 16–19, 2013, Natal, Brazil
- "A Mixed Integer Programming Model for a Hybrid Flowshop Scheduling Problem with Limited Buffers", with P, L. Miranda Lugo and R. Texeira. In: XLV Brazilian Symposium on Operations Research. September 16–19, 2013, Natal, Brazil
- "Vehicle routing for recyclable waste collection", with E. Toso. In: XLIV Brazilian Symposium on Operations Research. September 24–28, 2012. Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

References _

Raf Jans

Professor in Logistics and Operations Management Chair in Supply Chain Operations Planning · HEC Montréal (Canada)

☑ raf.jans@hec.ca · 📞 +1 514 340 7256

Yossiri Adulyasak

Associate Professor in Logistics and Operations Management Canada Research Chair in Supply Chain Analytics · HEC Montréal (Canada)

y yossiri.adulyasak@hec.ca ⋅ **** +1 514 340 7029

Reinaldo Morabito

Professor in Production Engineering Federal University of São Carlos (Brazil)